[Music]
i know i know
this has to be the millionth tutorial on
how to draw hands that you're watching
at this point
since you've all been asking for it
lately cause my name is marcel and today
you're gonna learn how to draw hands
like a sir this video was a
week-long effort with all kinds of
visual aids i gave it my all and i hope
it helps you guys out that's all i have
to say for the intro the only thing
i might need to mention is that drawing
is a process
so after you watch this video you know
the theory but you still need to get
down the muscle memory as well
no tutorial out there can replace actual
practice
also i've been thinking about doing like
an xxl tutorial
with all kinds of different poses and
perspectives and
wrinkles difference between male female
and children but this video would amount
to
weeks of work maybe i'll do that as some
kind of big milestone special or
something
alright that's it enough with the
introduction let's just jump right into
it
you guys know my tutorials go by now i
try to explain things as beginner
friendly as possible
by taking something and breaking it
apart into its most simple shapes
that's the easiest and best way to learn
how to draw hands as a beginner
you want to learn how to draw something
then you first need to know how it's
built
one of the greatest artists of a modern
time
once said first an artist must
concentrate and visualize his concept
that's right and you can't visualize
your hand if you don't know
anything about it so let's start from
the beginning
step 1 in drawing a hand is always
drawing a simple brick for the base of
the hand
and to that i just add some stickman
fingers and a thumb
now in today's video i'll show you how
to draw fingers the thumb
and the back of the hand as well as the
palm i split it into those
three chapters because if you can draw
those three things
you'll be able to draw a hand at least
in theory
well let's start with the fingers
because
well we're gonna start somewhere right
so here well here are my
fingers and one of my fingers consists
of
three equally long parts
that's precisely the reason why i draw
hands like this
with three different strokes
i know how mundane this sounds but
believe me this makes a huge
difference and i think this becomes a
lot more apparent when drawing fingers
sideways like i said your finger
consists of three
equally long parts just keep in mind
that the fingertip is round
since this part of our skeleton is
shorter and round as well
now the top part of the fingertip is not
because you still have your thumbnail on
that side
i don't know about you but to me this
looks a lot more organic than just
drawing in some round shape and hoping
that it kinda resembles a finger
but i have to admit for quick sketches i
draw fingers
just with a couple of simple strokes as
well and it's not
wrong per se every volume of my manga
series
had at least a couple of pages where i
drew fingers like that
but even then i checked my drawings by
measuring if the fingers are too long or
too short
that way even fingers that aren't very
detailed would look
acceptable but make no mistake if your
finger has
three equal parts depends on how you
look at it
don't measure it from the knuckle
measure it the way i did before
for the sake of simplicity we'll say
that the knuckle still belongs to the
back
of the hand not to the finger that way
all three parts are still
in equal size speaking of which i think
i
might need a trip to the hospital right
now
now that was the first level i hope you
guys all understand how to draw fingers
now
since i sacrificed my middle finger for
it i hope that was worth it i'll show
you the thumb at the end of the video
don't worry
you guys will understand why when the
time comes so there's only one
thing left to do let's continue by
drawing the palm and the back of the
head
when it comes to the back of the hand
there's not a lot that i could tell you
the most important part will be
the paw the only important parts at the
back of the hand
are the knuckles and the tendons your
knuckles aren't placed in a straight
line here they are placed in a
fan shape if you pay attention you can
see how this fan shape consists
even with your fingers and where can you
check there
right at the joints where we split the
fingers apart earlier
now one last thing when it comes to the
back of the hand
your bones and tendons all originate
from one
point in fact your tendons
lie on top of your bones and that's
precisely why you don't draw the
knuckles round but more edgy
so you don't actually draw the knuckles
here but rather the tendons that lie on
top
yeah and that's about it when it comes
to the back of the hand
let's flip right over to the pod now
let's split the palm into its
single components as well we've got your
tenor
that's the heel of the hand then there's
your hypotenure and then there's
uh well this part has no medical terms
since there's no muscles or anything
here
so you can call it steve or whatever i
care but for the sake of this video
just call it the base of the fingers
but to be honest i think this still
looks way too complicated after all i
want to make this tutorial as beginner
friendly as possible
so let's make the palm even simpler
i know i can hear you guys moan nobody
cares about the palm of the hand
the fingers are the difficult part not
the palm
but once you're drawing hands sideways
or in
another way you'll find yourself
struggling a lot if you don't know how
the palm works
so yeah i'm sorry there's no way around
it but it's not that bad
since you only need to learn these three
parts in order to draw a palm and
visualize it
and we all know that an artist has to
concentrate and visualize his concepts
that's pretty much it for the palm as
well the most important thing
was the heel of the hand since it's
directly connected to the thumb
and that's why i wanted to show you the
thumb at the end
[Music]
you know i used to draw the thumb as an
oval shape on top of the heel
but as you can guess this isn't exactly
anatomically correct if you take a
closer look you can see that your thumb
has a middle part to it as well
just like your regular finger maybe it's
a bit understandable
if i'll show it to you guys from another
perspective as well
just always check if it still consists
of three parts and you are good to go
and now that you know all three parts in
theory you only need to practice with it
if you want to get started with drawing
hands just take it from me
like you guys know i started with a
brick and some stick figure fingers
and then i had all the things we learned
in the past
6 or 7 minutes but please don't expect
to draw perfect hands after this video
like i said you now know the theory but
you might still lack the practice
for some people it works out right away
others still might need to practice
and that's okay everyone has their own
learning speed this ain't a race after
all
the only thing you need to learn by
heart is the way the hand is constructed
here have a cheat sheet with all the
relevant infos you need
and while we're at it why don't we make
a deal out of this
you can screenshot this sheet and in
exchange you give this video a thumbs up
but despite everything if you still have
problems with drawing hands
there are a couple of ways to help you
out okay maybe this looks dumb at first
but if you really
struggle with drawing hands you can just
mock your hands the way i did on my
cheat sheet earlier
and my personal opinion this method is
so underrated and it could really help
you out
like i said in my last video there are
tons of people who prefer 3d models or
maybe wooden anatomy puppets which is
fine i'm happy if it works out for you
but you guys know me i'm a fan of the
old school method
of searching for real life photos online
i just think this method works out the
best
and it's the cheapest speaking of it if
you missed it you can watch my last
tutorial it's all about perspective and
it works out with drawing hands as well
so just give it a shot i've linked it on
the top right corner
before you leave please make sure that
you screenshot of the cheat sheet
i showed you earlier it's pretty
important i mean if i didn't quote mr
squarepants enough times in this video
already
i'm gonna do it one last time an artist
has got to
i think that might have been the wrong
quote anyway
if you wonder what kinds of pens and
erasers i use you can just go ahead and
check my website
i listed and linked it all there and who
knows maybe i'll actually do an xxl
hands tutorial at some point so you
might want to stick around for that
well then my name is marcel and i am
very glad we have universal healthcare
in germany reattaching fingers included
although i
might need to check that just give me a
sec i'll see you in the next video bye
[Music]
hey